Finding Aid for Kenneth H. MacDonald Papers, 1932-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kenneth H. MacDonald Papers 1932-1989
MacDonald, Kenneth H. (Kenneth Hugh), 1921-1989.
90135 Aa 2; Ac
Owner and operator of a network of Michigan radio stations, including WSAM in Saginaw, Michigan. Biographical files relating in part to his Ann Arbor and Saginaw, Michigan, civic activities; scrapbooks, advertisements and other materials relating to WSAM radio station; files detailing his involvement with the National Association of Broadcasters; scrapbooks documenting career activities, and photographs.
2 linear feet in 3 boxes
2 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received in October 1989 from Mrs. Kenneth H. MacDonald (Donor No. 7733 ).
The collection is open to research.
Kenneth Hugh MacDonald (1921-1989) was a dominant personality in broadcasting in Michigan from his arrival in 1947 to his death in May 1989. Born in Newton, Massachusetts, MacDonald graduated from the Leland Powers School of Theater in Boston in 1942. He enlisted shortly after his graduation and served five years as a U.S. Navy pilot in World War II. In 1947, after brief employ as a magazine advertising manager in Alabama, MacDonald settled in Ann Arbor, where he worked as a sales representative for station WPAG-AM. While in Ann Arbor, he was active in the Ann Arbor Civic Theater, the Republican City Committee, Junior Chamber of Commerce, and Catholic Family Services. He also extended his activities at WPAG to include his own radio show, "FM-Club," beginning in 1948.
In 1962, MacDonald purchased the Saginaw radio station WSAM, formerly owned by Mr. Milton Greenebaum, and eventually built this investment into a family network that is now the largest broadcasting firm based in Michigan. The holdings of the MacDonald Broadcasting Company include: WSAM-AM and WKCQ-FM (Saginaw); WATT-AM and WLZ-FM (Cadillac); WILS-AM and WKKP-FM (Lansing); and WWPZ-AM and WMBN-FM (Petoskey). In addition to his involvement in radio at the local level, MacDonald was also involved at the state and national levels. Long a member of the Michigan Association of Broadcasters, he was elected its president in 1974. He also brought his leadership capabilities to the National Association of Broadcasters, serving on its board of directors beginning in 1981, and playing an active part in two of its committees--the Radio Audience Measurement Task Force (RAMTF), and the Committee on Local Radio Audience Measurement (COLRAM)--both of which were formed in 1985.
In addition to his activities in radio, MacDonald was deeply devoted to his family and to his community. He and his wife, Ann, daughter of a Detroit lumber executive, had seven children, three of whom still are managing the company's stations in Saginaw, Cadillac, and Petoskey. MacDonald was a member of St. Stephen's Catholic Church, and he worked with many other service organizations in the Saginaw area, such as the United Way, American Red Cross, Chamber of Commerce, Voluntary Action Center, and Junior Achievement. He organized the first Saginaw River Raft Race (1974), and in 1979, became part owner of the Saginaw Gears hockey team (now Saginaw Hawks). In each of his activities, MacDonald left a distinct and significant mark. His contributions to Michigan broadcasting history are representative of the scope and depth of his dedication to community life.
The Kenneth Hugh MacDonald Papers consist of 2 linear feet of material in three boxes, two oversize volumes, and one oversize folder. The papers date from 1939 to 1989, but the bulk of the material falls between 1941-1961 and 1985-1989. The papers consist of five series: Biographical (1939-1989); WSAM Radio, Saginaw (1941-1961); National Association of Broadcasters (NAB) and Committees (1985-1989); Photographs (1941-1983); and Personal Scrapbooks (1939-1951).
Subjects:
Advertising.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); MacDonald Broadcasting Company.; National Association of Broadcasters.; Radio broadcasting--Michigan.; Saginaw (Mich.); WSAM (Radio station: Saginaw, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Bad Axe (Mich.); Broadcasting.; Fairs--Michigan--Saginaw County.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Radio industry--Michigan--Saginaw.; Saginaw (Mich.); Saginaw County Fair (Mich.); WLEW (Radio station: Bad Axe, Mich.); WSAM (Radio station: Saginaw, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series (0.3 linear feet) includes materials which give an excellent overview of MacDonald's family, career, and civic activities. Particularly helpful are the "Obituaries/Posthumous Accolades," as they provide a context for the other materials, which represent family and civic interests. The "Clippings--Career" file offers a comprehensive selection of information on MacDonald's career status and objectives over a broad period of time, including his bid for WSAM in 1962.
  - Ann Arbor Civic Theater 1951-1967 (Box 1)
  - Ann (Webb) MacDonald and Webb Family 1932-1944 (Box 1)
  - Catholic Charities and United Fund 1957-1960 (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - Ann Arbor (Miscellaneous) 1949-1961 (Box 1)
    - Kenneth Hugh MacDonald Career 1951-1987 (Box 1)
    - Saginaw (Miscellaneous) 1966-1980 (Box 1)
    - Saginaw River Raft Race 1974-1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - MacDonald Broadcasting Company, correspondence 1981-1989 (Box 1)
  - MacDonald Family in Radio (clippings) 1974-1986 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Association of Broadcasters 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries/Posthumous Accolades 1989 (Box 1)
  - President Ford Presentation May 1976 (Box 1)
  - Republican City Committee (Ann Arbor) 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - Saginaw Gears (hockey team) 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Speeches/Talks, ? to 1989 (Box 1)
- WSAM Radio, Saginaw
  The WSAM Radio, Saginaw series (0.6 linear feet, 2 oversize volumes, and 1 oversize folder) consists of materials that were inherited by MacDonald when he purchased the station. Included are "Program Schedules" dating from 1944 to 1947, and "Scrapbooks" dating from 1941 to 1961. The "Program Schedules" are an interesting sample of what was being offered on radio at that time. The "Scrapbooks," however, are the principal focus of the series, and they are rich with bits of information on broadcasting history in the state of Michigan. Presumably compiled by Mr. Greenebaum, all the scrapbooks follow roughly the same format. They include newspaper clippings regarding administrative events, local advertisements for radio shows, and other stations (radio and television) in the area; letters of thanks and praise; and photographs of station events, such as the WSAM booth at the Saginaw Fair. Only two of the scrapbooks (oversize volumes) are still intact. The rest of the scrapbooks have been separated into files of clippings and correspondence. Although somewhat cumbersome, the oversize scrapbooks are well-organized and should be helpful models when viewing the other, separated materials. The "Advertisements" in the oversize folder were compiled from the scrapbooks which were taken apart. Large and colorful, they complement the smaller newspaper ads for various radio shows. The photographs relating to WSAM under Greenebaum can be found in three locations: in this series, in the Photographs series, and in the oversize volumes.
  - Advertisements (Folder Ac)
  - Program Schedules March 1944-January 1947 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbooks and loose materials from scrapbooks
    - 1941-1944, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1944-1947 (Volume 1)
    - 1947-1948, 1 folders (Box 1)
    - 1947-1948 (Volume 2)
    - 1949-1953, 10 folders (Box 1)
    - 1954-1956, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1958-1961, 1 folders (Box 1)
- National Association of Broadcasters
  The National Association of Broadcasters series (0.4 linear feet) consists of the records produced and/or collected by MacDonald during his tenure on the NAB Board of Directors and two of its committees, the Committee on Local Radio Audience Measurement (COLRAM) and the Radio Audience Measurement Task Force (RAMTF). Not only do these records give a good perspective on MacDonald's contributions to broadcasting at the national level, but they also provide insight into the goals and priorities of the NAB, and particularly its effects on local broadcasting. MacDonald's position is most clearly evident in the correspondence. On the sending or receiving end, his influence is considerable.
  - NAB Board of Directors
    - Clippings 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1985-1989 (Box 1)
    - Memoranda 1985-1988 (Box 1)
    - State Leadership Conference (Washington, D.C.) February 1988 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Local Radio Audience Measurement (COLRAM)
    - Agendas and Minutes 1985-1988 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1985-1989 (Box 2)
    - Memoranda 1986-1988 (Box 2)
    - News Releases 1985-1987 (Box 2)
  - Radio Audience Measurement Task Force (RAMTF)
    - Agendas and Minutes 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1985-1987 (Box 2)
    - Final Report 1987 (Box 2)
    - Memoranda 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - News Releases 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Request for Proposals and List of Respondents 1985 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (0.2 linear feet) includes materials which relate directly to the first two series. The bulk of the photographs correspond to the WSAM scrapbooks (see description above). In addition, though, are images of the construction of buildings and towers for stations WSAM and WLEW (Bad Axe), 1948-1949. The remaining images relate to the Biographical series, and include pictures of MacDonald, his wife, and of various civic activities and events, including Ann Arbor Civic Theater productions and Vice President Nixon's visit to Ann Arbor in 1960.
  - Ann Arbor Civic Theater circa 1958 (Box 2)
  - Ann MacDonald Story (Saginaw News) August 1974 (Box 2)
  - Kenneth MacDonald (miscellaneous) undated (Box 2)
  - Saginaw Gears Award Presentation March 1983 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks (loose or removed) 1941-1961, 11 folders (Box 2)
  - Vice President and Mrs. Richard Nixon in Ann Arbor October 1960 (Box 2)
  - WSAM (Saginaw) and WLEW (Bad Axe) 1948-1949, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Personal Scrapbooks
  The Personal Scrapbooks series (0.5 linear feet) also relates directly to the Biographical series. Included here are materials which cover MacDonald's activities from 1939 to 1951, including his involvement in Leland Powers School theatrical productions, his role in the Broadway play "Junior Miss," his continuing involvement in theater during his service in the navy, and his first years in Ann Arbor.
  - 1939-1942, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 3)
  - 1941-1944, 1 volumes (Box 3)
  - 1946-1951, 1 volumes (Box 3)